Next we are going to talk about infant CPR which applies to any baby up to one
year old. Much like with older children, cardiac arrest in infants usually starts
as a respiratory issue rather than a heart problem. While the situation is
different, you will find that the core steps of the rescue remain the same ones
you have already learned. One, ensure the scene is safe before you approach. Two,
assess the infant for responsiveness. Because a baby can't tell you if they
are okay, you will check for a reaction by tickling the infant's foot or
pinching their toe. While you do this, check for breathing. Is their chest
rising and falling? Look for those severe signs we discussed earlier. A lack of
consciousness or blue lips and extremities. If the baby moves when you
tickle their foot, that is a great sign, but you should still call 911 if you
feel something is wrong. Three, call for help and activate 911. If the infant is
unresponsive and not breathing, call 911 immediately and place them on speaker
phones so you can begin CPR while talking to the dispatcher. There is one
major difference for infants if you are alone and do not have a phone. You should
perform five rounds of CPR first. If the baby is still unresponsive after those
rounds, pick the baby up and take them with you to find a phone or help. You
never want to leave an infant alone while you go to get assistance.